Guide to the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry Records
1956-2000
RG 107
Yale University Divinity School Library
7
(15 boxes)
The Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry (CESCM) was founded in 1987 to "in order to create new opportunities for involving students and campus ministries in the work to rebuild an ecumenical student Christian ministry in the United States." This record group contains material related to predecessor organizations and administrative files from CESCM from its inception in 1987 to 2000. The CESCM grew out of the National Ecumenical Student Christian Council (NESCC), which was preceeded by the National Ecumenical Student Conference (NESC) and the National Interim Committee (NIC). It has a relationship with global ecumenical student organizations through affiliate membership in the World Student Christian Federation.
Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of CESCM
Biographical / Historical
1981 Aug 11-22 WSCF General Assembly in CA
1981 Aug 21-25 National Ecumenical Student Conference (NESC) meets in Berkeley, CA
1981 National Interim Committee is formed
1983 Aug 11-15 2nd National Ecumenical Student Conference meets at University of Maryland, College Park
1983 Aug National Ecumenical Student Christian Council (NESCC) is formed
1985Jul-Aug NESCC General Assembly meets at DePaul University, Chicago
1986 Feb 12-16 Leadership Development Conference sponsored by NESCC
1986 Mar NESCC collapsed in March 1986, shortly after the WSCF Mexico General Assembly; the North America Regional Committee (NARC) was disbanded; WSCF North America region effectively ceased to exist.
1987 Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry is formed
1988 CESCM recommends that WSCF North America staff be retained for two year interim.
1990 Dec 28 - 1991 Jan 1 "Celebrate" Conference (1)
1994 Dec 28 - 1995 Jan 1 "Celebrate" Conference (2)
1995 CESCM was affiliated with the WSCF as a member movement, joining student Christian movements from more than 80 countries
1998 Dec 30 - 1999 Jan 3 "Celebrate" Conference (3)
Scope and Contents
The records document ecumenical student Christian work in the United States and are valuable for the way in which they complement other archival collections at the Divinity Library. Added to papers of Ruth Harris, Margaret Flory, John R. Mott, Clarence P. Shedd, Robert Wilder, Luther Wishard, Henry Burt Wright and others, as well as the archives of the World Student Christian Federation, Student Volunteer Movement, Student Christian Movement in New England, New England Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education, National Campus Ministry Association and YMCA Student Division, the CESCM archives provide a detailed picture of the development of religious work among college and university students in the United States.
Series I contains background material and documents of the predecessor organizations of the CESCM, including the National Ecumenical Student Christian Council. Series II documents the "Celebrate" conferences - ecumenical student conferences coordinated by the CESCM. See YDSL Record groups 46A anad 46B for additional documentation of the World Student Christian Federation North America Region, with which the CESCM was affiliated.
Series III contains general adminstrative records of the CESCM: committee records, financial reports, staff reports, etc. It is divided into several subseries: Subseries 1: CESCM in formation; Subseries 2: Partners group; Subseries; 3: Steering and Administrative Committees; Subseries 4: Financial Records; Subseries 5: Staff Reports; Subseries 6: Program Activities; Subseries 7: CESCM Publications; Subseires 8: Correspondence files.
There is some overlap between the various subseries because the records came from the files of different individuals, particularly Ruth Harris and Gayla Spicknall. Gayla Spicknall was the primary CESCM staff member in its New York office from 1987 until 1992, when she was stricken with cancer. Ruth Harris was a CESCM "partner" representing the United Methodist Church.
Arrangement
I. Predecessor and Related Organizations
II. Celebrate Conferences
III. CESCM Administrative Files
Church work with students; College students -- Religious life; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Educators; Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry
- Predecessor and Related Organizations, Series I
  - Misc. background documents incl. overview of United States Student Christian movements (1956); Constitution of WSCF(1973); By-laws of North American Regional Committee of WSCF (1975); "A Brief Research Sketch on the Goals and Objectives of the WSCF in North America" (ca. 1979); "Emerging from the Wilderness: Rebuilding an SCM in the United States" (ca. 1980), 1956-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Background articles on the demise of the University Christian Movement, 1969, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Planning for North America - Asia project (WSCF), 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Ecumenical Student Conference (NESC) - Steering Committee meetings and conference planning, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4, 5)
  - WSCF General Assembly, San Francisco, 1981 Aug (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
  - NESC planning, financial report, request for funding, mailing list, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - NESC Steering Committee: planning, minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Press release, news articles re. NESC, Berkeley meeting, 1981 Aug (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Reflections on the NESC" by John C. O'Brien (typescript mimeographed document); holograph anonymous reflection, ca. 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Statement of the Gay/Lesbian NESC Caucus"; info for workshop moderators; letter from National Ecumenical Movement of Puerto Rico; notes of Ruth Harris, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - NESC mailing list; list of WSCF delegates to NESC, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NESC Conference handbook; worship bulletin, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NESC / National Interim Committee (NIC)correspondence; WSCF NA Update, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Local Unit Development Manual - draft (Canadian SCM), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Interim Committee (NIC) Atlanta meeting; notes, correspondence of Ruth Harris, 1982 Jan (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - NIC / WSCF Church Relations Committee, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - NIC correspondence and reports, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - NIC correspondence and reports, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - NIC / WSCF Church Relations Committee, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - NESC II: letter to participants: "Building a multi-racial movement: resolutions", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - NESC II: preparatory material for participants: application, "Background Information", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Proposal for formation of National Ecumenical Student Christian Council (NESCC), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Post NESC correspondence re. formation of NESCC, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - NESCC Statement of Purpose and administration, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Reports from related movements, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - WSCF Universal Day of Prayer for Students, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - WSCF: "North American Region - Comments on Ten Years of Regionalization" by Judy Skinner in consultation with John Huot, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Korea Exchange - NESCC - EYC (Ecumenical Youth Council), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - NESCC Central Committee correspondence and minutes, 1983 Nov - 1984 Jul (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - NESCC Central Committee correspondence and minutes, 1984 Aug - Dec (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Regional activities: North Carolina Student Christian Movement, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
  - Regional activities: Summer work programs, etc., 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - NESCC financial records, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 42-44)
  - NESCC Central Committee - crisis; NESCC Advisory Committee, 1985 Jan - May (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - NESCC Planning Committee, 1985 Jun- Sep (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - NESCC General Assembly, 1985 Jul 31 - Aug 4 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Proposals, notes, corres. re. structure of NESCC, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - List of Regional / Organizational Contact Persons, 1986 Feb (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence of Gayla Spicknall, NESCC staff person, 1986 Jan - Sep (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Letter from Gayla Spicknell to Bill Ellis re. history and status of NESCC, enclosing Constitution, 1986 Oct 15 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - NESCC Leadership Development Conference Planning Committee, 1985 Nov- Dec (Box 4, Folder 52, 53)
  - NESCC Leadership Development Conference, 1986 Feb 12-16 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - NESCC Leadership Development Conference, 1986 Feb 12-16 (Box 5, Folder 55-60)
  - NESCC Denominational and Church Agency meeting, 1986 Oct 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - NESCC Reports / Program proposals, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - NESCC Newsletter, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - NESCC correspondence of Gayla Spicknell and Ruth Harris; WSCF NA correspondence of John O'Brien, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - NESCC meetings; Lutheran Student Movement national assembly, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - NESCC Financial records, budget, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Resources from the Student Christian Movement of Canada: Bible Studies, 1970s - 1980s (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Resources from the Student Christian Movement of Canada: Development manual, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 68)
- "Celebrate" Conferences, Series II
  - Pre-Celebrate
    - WSCF-U.S. Churches Celebration, New York City, 1985 Nov 17-18 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Celebrate 1990-1991
    - Celebrate - 1988 planning meeting (New York) incl. pre-meeting correspondence, 1988 Sep 30- Oct 1 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - 1989 planning meetings (Illinois, Tennessee, Kentucky), 1989 Jan, Apr, Oct (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - 1990 planning meetings (Illinois), 1990 Jan, Oct, Dec (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Planning: reports from CESCM Steering Committee, 1990 Sep 27-28 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Planning: WSCF: memos and correspondence, participants, Friends mailing list, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - International orientation, 1990 Dec 28 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Registration packet (Disciples of Christ), 1990 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Denominational promotions: American Baptist, Disciples of Christ, Episcopal, Lutheran, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Denominational promotions: Moravian, Presbyterian, United Methodist, United Church of Christ, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Ecumenical workshop application, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Worship Committee, incl. resources re communion, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Bible study development, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Bible study, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Program booklet for "Celebrate" - A National Ecumenical Gathering of Student Christian Conference - December 28, 1990 through January 1, 1991 at the Galt House, Louisville, Kentucky (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Financial records, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Funding: pre-grant correspondence, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Funding: Lilly proposal, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Fudning: Lilly correspondence, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Funding: correspondence, payments, receipts, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Funding: Friendship Press proposal, correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Funding: final report to Lilly, 1991 Apr 30 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Evaluation meeting (Chicago), 1991 Feb (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Publications: study booklet - correspondence and editing, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Publications: video - correspondence and editing, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Press: "Rattling the Dry Bones of the Student Christian Movement" by Donald G. Shockley, from The Christian Century, 1989 Nov 22 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Celebrate 94 Ecumenical Student Conference
    - Press, correspondence, program booklet: "Gathering at the Crossroads - A National Ecumenical Christian Students Gathering - December 28, 1994 through January 1, 1995 in St. Louis, Missouri, 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Celebrate III
    - Publicity, workshop information, program booklet: "back 2 faith: Faithful Living in a New Millennium - A National Ecumenical Christian Student Gathering - December 30, 1998 through January 3, 1999 in Ridgecrest, North Carolina, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 96)
- Administrative Files, Series III
  - CESCM in Formation
    - CESCM Constitution, Statement of Purpose, Roles and Relationships (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Development of CESCM, 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Planning Committee: minutes, correspondence, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Meetings of NESCC staff, Denominational and Church Agency staff, WSCF NA staff, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - "Campus Ministry / Global Ministry / WSCF NA Meeting" (Feb), " CESCM meeting (Nov), materials re. Presbyterian Church USA National Student Conference; CESCM Planning Consultation, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Partners group
    - CESCM Partners meetings; address list for CESCM Partners, 1988 Apr, Sep (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Partners meetings, financial reports, correspondence, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Partners meetings, Steering Committee meetings, staff reports, Report of the Project Team, budget, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Administrative Committee meetings, Partners meetings, Planning and Coordinating Committee meeting, meeting and proposals re. CESCM structure, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Special CESCM meetings: Jean Francois Deltiel; Structure Committee, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Partners' meetings, Staff reports, CESCM colloquy, Gayla Spicknall correspondence, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Partners' meetings, Gayla Spicknall correspondence, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Partners' meetings, 1994-1999 (Box 9, Folder 109-116)
  - Steering and Administrative Committees
    - Meetings, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 117-118)
    - Meetings; Proposal for a 1989 CESCM National Ecumenical Leadership Development Program for Students (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - Meetings, 1990-1993 (Box 10, Folder 120-122)
  - Financial Records
    - NESCC WSCF North America Account, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - Audit for United Ministries in Education, which provided treasury services for CESCM, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 124)
    - Letter re. United Methodist funds; CESCM financial report, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 125)
    - CESCM budget, reports, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 126)
    - Memo to denominational campus ministry executives re. CESCM funding; financial reports, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 127-128)
    - Memo to CESCM Partners re. funding; financial reports, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 129)
    - Memos from Episcopal Church; CESCM budget, financial reports, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 130)
    - Memo to CESCM Partners re. funding; financial reports, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Staff Reports
    - Reports from Gayla Spicknall; proposal re. conference, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 132)
    - Report from Gayla Spicknall; Report from Allan Burry, CESCM representative at WSCF Executive Committee meeting in Harare, Zimbabwe, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 133)
    - Reports from Gayla Spicknall, 1989-1992 (Box 10, Folder 134-137)
  - Program Activities
    - European Student Chaplains' Conferences, 1989-1992 (Box 10, Folder 138-140)
    - European Student Chaplains' Conference, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 141)
    - CESCM Colloquy, 1992 Oct (Box 11, Folder 142)
    - Solidarity Brigade to Cuba, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 143, 144)
    - Ecumenical Global Gathering of Youth and Students (EGGYS) - updates, correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 11, Folder 145)
    - EGGYS - reports, background papers, 1991-1993 (Box 11, Folder 146)
    - EGGYS - minutes of planning committee, 1989-1993 (Box 11, Folder 147)
    - EGGYS - reports, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 148)
    - EGGYS - newsletters, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 149)
  - CESCM Publications
    - CESCM web site printouts: CESCM homepage, "History of the SCM in the USA", CESCM brochure, list of CESCM partners, other links; CESCM printed brochure, 1995-2000 (Box 11, Folder 150)
    - CESCM web site printouts: WSCF information, WSCF directory, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 151)
    - CESCM web site printouts: Reports on the Work and Gatherings of the WSCF and its Member SCMs, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 152)
    - CESCM web site printouts: Past and Present Celebrate Conference Information, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 153)
  - CESCM Correspondence Files
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall, 1987-1988 (Box 12, Folder 154-158)
    - Financial Correspondence, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 158a)
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 159-162)
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 163-166)
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall, 1991 Jan-1992 Mar (Box 14, Folder 167-173)
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall, 1992 Apr-Dec (Box 15, Folder 174-176)
    - Correspondence primarily to/from Gayla Spicknall re. WSCF Regional office, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 177)